<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Six dreadfull alarms in order to the right improving of the gospel ro [sic] the substance of a sermon / preached by Mr. Michael Bruce, Minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Bruce, Michael, 1634 or 5-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77711</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5220B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173194</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45504365</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45504365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171666</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77711)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171666)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2584:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Six dreadfull alarms in order to the right improving of the gospel ro [sic] the substance of a sermon / preached by Mr. Michael Bruce, Minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Bruce, Michael, 1634 or 5-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew, VII, 24 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, Scottish --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171666:1"/>
            <p>SIX DREADFULL ALARMS IN ORDER TO THE RIGHT IMPROVING OF THE GOSPEL, RO THE SUBSTANCE OF A SERMON</p>
            <p>Preached by Mr. <hi>Michael Bruce</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 7.24</hi>
               </bibl> Therefore whoſoever heareth theſe Sayings of Mine, and doth them. I will liken him unto a Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which Built his Houſe upon a Rock: <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:171666:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:171666:2"/>
            <head>THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 7.24.</hi>
                  </bibl> Therefore whoſoever heareth theſe Sayings of Mine, and doth them, I will liken him unto a Wiſe-man which Built his Houſe upon a Rock: <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THERE is Two <hi>Questions</hi> I would Propone to you the Day, and I deſire an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to them both: The Firſt <hi>Question</hi> I would Propone to you, is this, <hi>What have ye done with all CHRISTs Sayings that ye have heard? And what have ye done with all the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ye have gotten? Have ye letten them all go by you as things that ye have no more adoe with? Or are ye among the number of theſe, that is Hearers and Doers?</hi> I trow when then the <hi>Queſtion</hi> comes to your Door, it ſhall put ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you in a Gaſt; <hi>What have ye done with all CHRISTs Sayings? And what have ye done with all the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that has been preached among you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Second <hi>Question</hi> I would Propone to you the Day, and that is, <hi>How are ye fitted for a Streſs of Weather that is coming by the Preachings that ye have heard?</hi> Here is a ſtrange <hi>ſtreſs of weather, the Rain falls, the Floods deſcends, and the Wind blows;</hi> that is an uncouth <hi>ſtreſs of weather,</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſtreſs of weather</hi> that many dyes in the midſt of it and wins never to the ſhore: The <hi>ſtorm</hi> is to fall upon <hi>Godlineſs account,</hi> and the <hi>ſtorm</hi> is to fall upon <hi>Religions account:</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:171666:3"/>This is the Houſe that ye have been Building. And now the <hi>Queſtion</hi> I Propone, is, <hi>Whether or no have ye this made ſure, and founded upon a Rock?</hi> when the <hi>ſtreſs of weather</hi> comes, that it may ſtand and not move: That I may put you to it, to prepare for <hi>a streſs of weather,</hi> therefore I have choſen this Text. In the former part of this Chapter, our <hi>Maſter</hi> hath laid many very concerning Truths at this Peoples Door, and He ſhuts up all His long Preachings with this, as if it were the moſt concerning Truths of all. <hi>Therefore whoſoever hears theſe Sayings of Mine, and doth them, I will liken him to a Wiſe man which Built his Houſe upon a Rock:</hi> &amp;c. which is the words of my Text; Wherein ye have theſe <hi>three things</hi> conſiderable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> A <hi>Duty</hi> ſuppoſed, or rather Propoſed; which is <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>doing</hi> by the People of GOD. 2. Ye have that <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> Commended, and it is Commended from both. <hi>Firſt,</hi> From the <hi>advantagiouſneſs</hi> of it. 2. It is Commended by laying it over forgainſt the oppoſite of it: for then a thing ſhines ay beſt, when it is laid over forgainſt the oppoſite.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Third</hi> Thing is, The Way how this comes in with <hi>a there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: Therefore whoſoever hears theſe Sayings of Mine, &amp; doth them, I will liken him to a Wiſe-man which Built his Houſe upon a Rock:</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Illustration</hi> of this <hi>Similitude,</hi> I ſhall ſpeak more particularly to it, as I go throw the <hi>Doctrine:</hi> I ſhall here give you ſome few <hi>Obſervations</hi> from the <hi>Connexion,</hi> &amp; then come to the words more particularly.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Firſt Obſervation</hi> from the <hi>Connexion</hi> ſhall be this, That it is the Goodneſs of our <hi>Maſter</hi> to His <hi>Followers,</hi> that as He gives them <hi>Preaching,</hi> ſo He <hi>Schools</hi> them in the right uſe making of <hi>preaching:</hi> Or ye may take it thus, That as our <hi>Maſter</hi> deſires to have His People <hi>hearing,</hi> ſo He will have them ſchooled in the right improvement of <hi>Preaching</hi> when
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171666:3"/>heard. Therefore this Leſſon about <hi>right improvement of Preaching</hi> is the thing that He ſhuts up all this Excellent <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> with: Therefore, this is the Great Buſſineſs ye have adoe, as to <hi>hear preaching,</hi> ſo to <hi>improve preaching.</hi> Well then, that I may ſpeak a little to this; I will let you ſee from the <hi>Text,</hi> comparing it with the <hi>Context,</hi> what Way CHRIST <hi>Schools</hi> His <hi>Hearers</hi> in the <hi>right uſe making of preaching.</hi> 2. I ſhall let you ſee wherefore CHRIST takes pains to <hi>School</hi> His People <hi>in the right improvement of preaching.</hi> 3. We ſhall give you a Word or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> and go forward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt then,</hi> How <hi>Schools</hi> He His People <hi>in the right uſe making of Preachings?</hi> Ye will ſee Him from the <hi>Text,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether from the <hi>Context, Schooling</hi> them Two Ways. <hi>Firſt,</hi> By giving them <hi>Dreadfull Alarms.</hi> 2. By giving them <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Instructions:</hi> And therefore, and ye will take a view of my Text, ye will find ſix <hi>Alarms</hi> in it, and all <hi>for improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Preaching;</hi> and gife ye will take a view of my Text, ye will find ſix <hi>Inſtructions</hi> for <hi>the right improving of Preaching;</hi> and as ye will be anſwerable to the Great GOD for the <hi>Preachings</hi> ye hear, take both the <hi>Alarms,</hi> and the <hi>Inſtructions</hi> with you.</p>
            <p>The <hi>First Alarm</hi> that lyes in the boſom of my <hi>Text,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Context,</hi> is this, That People may be living un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Preaching Miniſtry</hi> all their Days, and yet when all is done, CHRIST and they never ken other. O! then take home the <hi>Alarm,</hi> and be not ye among that number; take the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm</hi> home, and <hi>improve Preaching</hi> better. O ſirs! may theſe two ſtand together living under a <hi>Preaching Ministry</hi> all their Days, and yet CHRIST and they never ken other; Should not this be an <hi>Alarm</hi> to you to <hi>improve preaching</hi> better.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Second Alarm</hi> lying in the boſom of my <hi>Text</hi> worthy of your Obſervation, and that is, That People may get a <hi>Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:171666:4"/>unner the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and under <hi>Preaching,</hi> that may ſtick to them, not only throw a <hi>ſtorm,</hi> but may gang in to Eternity with them, and no leſs than Eternal <hi>Rejection</hi> convincing them of that; and then that <hi>Deluſion</hi> is our of time. GODS Eternal Wrath and Vengeance in Hell will be the firſt Cure that ſome of your <hi>Deluſions</hi> will get. There may be a <hi>Deluſion</hi> blecked in your boſom under the Preaching, that not only will go to Death, or a ſtorm with you, but it may gang into Eternity with you; and GODs Wrath in Hell the Cure of it: This may be a <hi>Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Alarm</hi> to you.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Third Alarm</hi> I ſhall give you from the Text, and it is this, There is a <hi>ſtreſs of weather</hi> coming, and as ye would be out of it, <hi>improve preaching</hi> better: for very few will bide it out; but the Man that <hi>improves preaching.</hi> Here is an uncouth <hi>Streſs of Weather coming, the Rain falling, the Floods deſcending, the Wind blowing,</hi> and the Man that <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves not preaching,</hi> he is like the Man which <hi>built his houſe upon the ſand, and whenever this ſtreſs of weather comes, his houſe falls:</hi> This may be an uncouth <hi>Alarm</hi> to you, to put you to <hi>improve preaching</hi> better.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Fourth Alarm</hi> to put you to <hi>improve preaching</hi> in the boſom of my Text, is this, That Folk may be a Work, and at meikle Work under <hi>preaching</hi> for building of a <hi>Houſe,</hi> and yet when all is done, loſs both their Profit and Pains: Here is a <hi>Great Work,</hi> it comes to a <hi>Houſe Building,</hi> it comes to the Ripeneſs of a <hi>Houſe,</hi> and yet Pains and Profit and all is loſt, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the <hi>Storm</hi> comes, the <hi>Houſe</hi> goes on, becauſe it is not Builded on a <hi>Rock.</hi> This may be a <hi>Dreadfull Alarm</hi> to you to <hi>improve preaching</hi> better, and to Build upon a <hi>Rock;</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which ye loſs both your Profit and your Pains: This may be a <hi>Dreadfull Alarm</hi> to you to be upon your <hi>Watch-tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and to ſee what yeill do with the <hi>Preachings</hi> that ye hear: For ye may be at miekle Pains and Travel to hear a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171666:4"/>
               <hi>Preaching,</hi> and Venture your Life for it, and yet when all is done, the <hi>storm</hi> may ding all down, and ye loſs both your Work and your Pains; This may be a <hi>Dreadfull Alarm</hi> to you.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Fifth Alarm</hi> lying in the boſom of my Text, and that is, That Folk may have their Light bettered by <hi>Preaching,</hi> and Folk may win at a bigg Profeſſion under <hi>Preaching,</hi> and yet when all is done, they and their Profeſſion both bulk little in CHRISTs Boſom; and their Light and their Profeſſion both be caſten over the Bar, and themſelves at the taill of it: Here they are Enlightened Folk, for they can ſay, <hi>LORD, LORD,</hi> they could not have ſaid that, if they had not been taught it by <hi>Preaching:</hi> Their Profeſſion is likeways made bigg by it, for they themſelves, and all the Country-ſide takes them for the Servants of GOD, and yet CHRIST <hi>profeſsed that He never knew them:</hi> This may be a <hi>Dreadfull Alarm</hi> to you.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Last Alarm,</hi> is this, That it is not Single Perſons on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that is in this Condition; but they are many of them, and ſince they are many of them, look that ye be not among the Multitude; and not only will they be many of them, but theſe many would give all the World to have one <hi>Preaching</hi> again to <hi>improve</hi> better, and it will be denied to them. Thir poor Bodies that cryed, <hi>LORD, LORD, open to us,</hi> would have given all the World for a Day of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> again; but it was gone, and there was no more Time for them. May not this be a Word of Warning to you, to try how ye guide <hi>preaching,</hi> for all theſe <hi>ſix Alarms</hi> lyes at your Door; They are CHRISTs <hi>Alarms</hi> to you from His Word; and I think then, ſince they are given you from CHRISTs own Word, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of you ſhould take them Home, and ſtart to your feet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Ye will find Six <hi>Instructions</hi> lying in the Boſom of my Text, for your guiding of <hi>preaching.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:171666:5"/>
            <p> And the <hi>First</hi> is this, Never think ye the <hi>Work of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is done, when the <hi>preaching</hi> is ended; for when the <hi>preaching</hi> is ended, your <hi>work</hi> about the <hi>preaching</hi> is but to begin: Therefore our <hi>Maſter</hi> tells them at the ending of this Excellent Sermon, that their <hi>Work</hi> was before their hand; <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> was but to begin: The <hi>Streſs of Work,</hi> and <hi>the Streſs of Weather</hi> was before their hand. It is a ſore matter Sirs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you, you think your ſelves well enough exonered at GODs Hand on a <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> that ye have heard two bits of <hi>preachings</hi> ſuch as they are; for ye have heard a bit of a ſtolen <hi>preaching</hi> ſome Night, and ye think your <hi>Work</hi> is done; but when the <hi>preaching</hi> is done, your <hi>Work</hi> is but to begin. O but I love the <hi>Hearer of a preaching</hi> well on a <hi>Sabbath-day,</hi> that ay the nearer night it grows, his <hi>Work</hi> grows the thronger upon his hand; And I like that <hi>Improver of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> well after a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> that divides the Week, and the firſt part of it he <hi>improves</hi> for the uſe making of what he hath heard; and the ſecond part oftit, he <hi>improves</hi> for preparing, and fitting himſelf for what he is to hear the next <hi>Sabbath-day.</hi> O Sirs, <hi>Are there any Dividers of the Week among you? Did ye ever divide the Week in two, for right improving of preaching?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Second Inſtruction,</hi> is this, Then <hi>preaching is rightly improven,</hi> when <hi>improven</hi> for bringing you the nearer CHRIST. The <hi>Hearer</hi> and the <hi>Doer,</hi> he is ay upon the height of the <hi>Rock</hi> with it, he is ay building himſelf on CHRIST, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming himſelf to Him: For my part Sirs, I love not the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of preaching</hi> that many Folk hath; for hear <hi>preaching</hi> as they will; <hi>Nearneſs</hi> to CHRIST is never ſtudied by them.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Third Inſtruction</hi> for <hi>right improving of preaching,</hi> and that is, When <hi>preaching</hi> is well <hi>improven,</hi> when <hi>improven</hi> for fitting Folk for <hi>foul-weather,</hi> that thereby they will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for a <hi>ſtreſs of weather,</hi> ſo that when that comes, their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171666:5"/>Ship ſhall be ſound below their Maſt ſtrong, their Taklings faſt, and their Sails ſpread, gang the World as it will.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Fourth Inſtruction,</hi> is this, Then <hi>Preachings</hi> is well <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proven,</hi> when <hi>improven</hi> for bettering and building of a <hi>houſe</hi> for CHRIST in thy boſom; <hi>preaching</hi> is never well <hi>impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> but when there is ſome pinning put in this his <hi>Houſe,</hi> or ſome ſtones laid on the Wall, or ſomething done thereby for putting forward the <hi>Houſe</hi> for CHRIST in thy boſom: Well, what is the reſult of the many <hi>preachings</hi> heard in this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; Folk gets the Time put off, in telling over Tales out of <hi>preachings</hi> that they hear; but few of them <hi>improven</hi> for <hi>building a Houſe for CHRIST</hi> in their boſom. There is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of this kind done by hearing of <hi>preaching</hi> among them: <hi>Preaching</hi> is never well <hi>improven,</hi> as long as a <hi>Houſe for CHRIST</hi> in thy boſom is not going up by <hi>preaching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Then <hi>preaching</hi> is well <hi>improven,</hi> when every <hi>preaching</hi> thou hears ſhines in thy <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> betwixt <hi>Sabbaths.</hi> I love that <hi>improver of a preaching</hi> well, that Folk will not need to Spear what the <hi>Miniſter</hi> was on in the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath;</hi> for it ſhines forth in his <hi>Practice</hi> through the Week; What need you Spear what the <hi>Minister</hi> was on in the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath?</hi> read it in yon mans <hi>practice</hi> throw the Week; <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> was much preſſed on the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> See ye it not engraven on you Mans <hi>Walk</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> through the Week. <hi>Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-mindedneſs</hi> has been much preſſed on the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> ſee ye it not in you Mans <hi>Walk</hi> and <hi>Converſation,</hi> as if he were in Heaven already. <hi>Mortification</hi> has been much preſſed on the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> ſee ye it not in you Mans uſing the <hi>World,</hi> as if he were hanged to the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> hanged unto him.</p>
            <p>Then Laſtly, <hi>Preachings</hi> are well <hi>improven,</hi> when <hi>impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> for ſitting us as for that day, (What day?) that day men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the 22. verſe, CHRIST calls it <hi>that Day Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings is well improven,</hi> when <hi>improven</hi> for fitting us for <hi>that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171666:6"/>Day,</hi> when we muſt all appear before the <hi>Tribunal</hi> of GOD; ſo that whenever we come, we ſhall be Welcome: When our <hi>Maſter</hi> will Welcome <hi>Laſses</hi> and <hi>Lads</hi> for <hi>improving preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and take them in by and clap their heads, and ſay, <hi>Well done good and faithfull Servant,</hi> I never loſt a <hi>preaching</hi> by you; and I never loſt a <hi>preaching</hi> by thee, thou gathered it ay up to the leaſt Crumb. It is a ſtrange thing to me Sirs, CHRIST will be at the Day of Judgement with them before e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he hath done with his <hi>Preaching,</hi> to tell us this much, that every <hi>preaching</hi> we hear, we may not have our acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to make with JESUS CHRIST when we appear there. Well then, theſe are the ſix <hi>Alarms</hi> upon the one hand, and ſix <hi>Inſtructions</hi> on the other hand for <hi>right improving of preaching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second Thing</hi> to be ſpoken to, is, Wherefore doth our <hi>Maſter</hi> take ſo much Pains to <hi>School</hi> us His <hi>Hearers</hi> in the <hi>right improving of preaching?</hi> It is upon two Accounts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Upon this Account, That all that he doth, and ſaith, is loſt Labour, except it be <hi>improven:</hi> And do ye think that ever our <hi>Maſter</hi> will take it well off a Peoples Hand to have all His <hi>Preachings</hi> loſt, and all His Pains loſt? <hi>Will He take it off your hand well</hi> (think ye) <hi>to have all His Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Preachings on Sabbath-days loſt? Will He take it well off your hand to have Fast-days-preachings, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion days-preachings loſt? And will He take it well off your hand to have many a stolen nights preaching that we have gone far for, and ventured your Life for loſt?</hi> But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, we have loſt all; <hi>What will come of us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He is ſerious: For it is upon this Account, that he may teſtifie to all His <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Followers,</hi> that the <hi>right Guiders of Preaching,</hi> is ay bulkſom in His Boſom: but all the Pains thou takes upon <hi>hearing of preaching</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>doing,</hi> will never make thee bulkſom in CHRISTs boſom,</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:171666:6"/>
            <p> The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I would have you to make of it, is this, Will ye tell me, Sirs, Have ye been at CHRISTs <hi>School</hi> yet? Have ye heard all theſe ſix <hi>Alarms,</hi> and taken them home for your <hi>miſimproving of Preaching?</hi> And have ye made uſe of all the ſix <hi>Inſtructions</hi> for that ſame end, and travelled through them all. But if ye will take a view of my Text more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, ye will find two things very remarkable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> muſt be reaſoned into <hi>the right improvement of Preaching,</hi> ere ever he fall on it: Ye muſt reaſon your ſelves into that Exerciſe. So CHRIST here, He begins this Verſe with <hi>a Therefore;</hi> Holding out a Reaſon for that Concluſion of <hi>doing,</hi> at the back of <hi>hearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Ye will ſee this in my Text, That ye muſt ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more keep the Loveſomneſs of <hi>doing,</hi> or the Loveſom ſide of <hi>doing</hi> in your Eye; or ye will grow <hi>ill-improvers of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> And therefore here He caſts up the Beautifull-ſide of that Exerciſe to them: The Man that <hi>hears</hi> and <hi>does,</hi> he is <hi>like a Man that builds his Houſe upon a Rock;</hi> and what ever <hi>ſtorm</hi> comes, his <hi>Houſe</hi> ſtands, &amp;c. Telling us this much, that, and we keep not the Beautifull-ſide of <hi>doing</hi> in our Eye, we are fair to be ſhaken in a day of the <hi>Croſs.</hi> But we come to the Words more particularly.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt</hi> from the <hi>Duty</hi> impoſed, or rather propoſed, and that is, <hi>Hearing</hi> and <hi>Doing</hi> by the People of GOD: And the <hi>Obſervation,</hi> is this, That it is a <hi>Duty</hi> that the LORD layes at all your Doors that hears the Goſpel, to be <hi>doing</hi> as well as <hi>hearing;</hi> Ye muſt do His <hi>Sayings,</hi> as well as ye muſt <hi>hear</hi> them, John 13.17. <hi>If ye know theſe things, happy are ye if ye do them.</hi> The <hi>Obſervation</hi> imports two things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Obſervation</hi> imports this, That Bleſſed JESUS has knit <hi>Hearing</hi> and <hi>Doing</hi> together, and ſince He has knit them together, GODs Vengeance will be upon that Man that will looſe that Knot, ſince He has knit <hi>Hearing</hi> and <hi>Doing</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:171666:7"/>together: Therefore upon your Immortal Souls peril, do not ye break that Knot: For He has knit <hi>Hearing</hi> and <hi>Doing</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and upon your Peril be it, i. ye undoe what He hath done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It imports this much, That it is a <hi>Doing-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> or the <hi>Christian</hi> that <hi>does beſt,</hi> is ay bulkſome in CHRISTS Boſom. Well now that I may ſpeak a little to this, for I think it is the Plague of <hi>Scotland;</hi> whatever <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> we <hi>hear,</hi> there is no <hi>doing</hi> among us: And therefore I ſay; that I may ſpeak a little to this: I'll <hi>Firſt</hi> Let you ſee what <hi>doing</hi> is, that ye muſt be at, if ſo be ye would be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of GOD: For there is meikle <hi>doing</hi> among many Folk, that Ille no give meikle Silver for. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall ſpeak a word to this. Wherein lyes the Commendableneſs of this, <hi>to be doing CHRISTs Sayings. Thirdly,</hi> I ſhall give you a word of <hi>Caution.</hi> And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> A word of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe;</hi> and go forward.</p>
            <p>The <hi>First</hi> Thing then to be ſpoken to, <hi>What is this</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>that they ſhould be at?</hi> It is a <hi>doing</hi> of the <hi>Sayings</hi> of CHRIST with theſe ſeven. O ken ye <hi>the doing of the Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of CHRIST</hi> that hath theſe <hi>ſeven</hi> with it? <hi>First,</hi> It is a Doing upon the back of Hearing of CHRISTs Sayings, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in all his Doings, labours ay to be Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the <hi>Rock</hi> CHRIST, and brought near Him; and if ye be not Labouring by your Doing, to be brought near the <hi>Rock,</hi> and conformed to Him, Ille not give a gray Groat for your Doing; Ille no give meikle Silver for many Folks Doing: For they never win to Conformity to CHRIST by their Doing. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is ſuch a Doing upon the back of Hearing of CHRISTs Sayings, whereby not only a Good Foundation is laid, but the fulneſs of the meaſure of the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a perfect man in CHRIST is aimed at by the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> as well as the laying of a Good Foundation. For my part Sirs, I think it is a poor Buſſineſs, we ſay ay we are Doing.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171666:7"/>
               <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and yet a Good Foundation is never laid by us, and we ſay that we are Doing-<hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and yet the Sydwall of a Buiding gangs never up with us; We ſay ay that we are Doing-<hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and yet the fulneſs of the meaſure of the ſtatures of CHRIST is not the End that we aim at in our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is ſuch a Doing upon the back of Hearing of CHRISTs <hi>Sayings,</hi> whereby at the back of thy Doing, thou Erects a New <hi>Walk,</hi> with theſe four cleaving to it: O have ye all theſe four cleaving to your <hi>Doing. Firſt,</hi> Such a <hi>Walk</hi> as hath <hi>Spiritual-mindedneſs</hi> in the midſt of it, Romams 8.1. <hi>Who Walk not after the Fleſh but after the Spirit.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every word of a Preaching that I get, I make Uſe of it for keeping me <hi>Spiritually-minded</hi> in my Generation, Philip. 3.20. <hi>Our Converſation is in Heaven, from whence we look for a Saviour. Why is thy Converſation in Heaven, poor Body?</hi> Even becauſe my <hi>Master</hi> is there, and where ſhould I be but where my <hi>Maſter</hi> is? A <hi>Second</hi> Thing that this <hi>Doer</hi> Erects, ye may take it out of Acts 9.31. <hi>Walking in the fear of the LORD, and the comfort of the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> Therefore my <hi>Walk</hi> hath ay two Flowers ſtrawed over it, <hi>the fear of the LORD, and the comforts of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and every one of them plays to others hands in my <hi>Walk.</hi> A <hi>Third</hi> Piece of <hi>Walk</hi> that this <hi>Doer</hi> Erects at the back of my <hi>Hearing,</hi> and that is in Micah 6.8. <hi>He Walks humbly with his GOD:</hi> And therefore ye ſhall never find my Head high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than the Duſt; and ye ſhall never find my Head higher than the Ground, <hi>humbly with my GOD ſhall my Walk be all my days.</hi> A Fourth <hi>Walk</hi> that is to be Erected upon the back of <hi>Hearing of CHRISTs Sayings,</hi> and that is, Such a <hi>Walk</hi> wherein the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hath <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Exactneſs</hi> engraven upon every ſtap of his <hi>Walk,</hi> 1 Peter 1.16 <hi>Be ye Holy, for I am Holy.</hi> The Men of the World ſays, What a ſorrow aills this Mans <hi>Holineſs,</hi> or that Mans <hi>Holineſs,</hi> that it may not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171666:8"/>gain you? There is no Mans <hi>Holineſs</hi> that we are to write af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for a Copy to us; but the <hi>Holineſs of GOD: Holy, as He is Holy,</hi> muſt be our aim. The Men of the World ſays, it is enough and we Profeſs to be <hi>holy:</hi> Yea, yea, in that day when CHRIST ſpeaks with Folk, if there be no more but a profeſſed <hi>holineſs,</hi> it will be caſten over the Bar, and themſelves at the taill of it. For I aſſure you <hi>holineſs</hi> bulks much in CHRISTs boſom; but a big Profeſſion make it as bony as ye like, will not bulk much in CHRISTs boſom, and there be no more. Theſe are the four <hi>Walks</hi> that ye are to Erect at the back of <hi>your hearing of CHRISTs Sayings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a <hi>Fourth</hi> Piece of <hi>Doing</hi> at the back of <hi>hearing</hi> that the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is to have, and that is, A <hi>doing</hi> with theſe three <hi>Harmonies</hi> in it. <hi>Firſt,</hi> A <hi>Harmony</hi> betwixt <hi>his</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the Duties of the Firſt Table of the Law, and his</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the Duties of the Second Table of the Law in his Walk;</hi> never one of them wrongs another, never one of them ſhuts another to the Door; but every one of them plays to others hands in his <hi>Walk</hi> and <hi>Practice:</hi> What think ye of that brave <hi>harmony?</hi> Few of you hath that excellent <hi>Walk in your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> A Second <hi>Harmony</hi> in this Mans <hi>Doing,</hi> and that is, A <hi>harmony</hi> betwixt his <hi>Light</hi> and his <hi>Practice,</hi> and never one of them Juſtels againſt another; he brings up his <hi>Practice</hi> to his <hi>Light,</hi> and never one of them thorturs with another: he lets no thorturing be betwixt theſe two: This may be the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our Mourning, that thorturing with <hi>Light</hi> is like to be <hi>Scotlands</hi> plague. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This Man keeps a <hi>harmony</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>his own part in doing, and GODs part in doing,</hi> and he never lets one of theſe croſes and thorturs anſwer, but he gives GOD the Glory of all his <hi>Doings;</hi> all the Supports, and all the Comforts, and all the Upholdings and throw bearings that GOD gives him, he gives GOD the Glory of it all; he ſteals nothing of GODs Glory from Him; but he levels all at
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171666:8"/>GODs Glory, and takes to himſelf Shame and Confuſion of Face: GODs Glory is the Butt we are to aim at in all our <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi> Therefore it is a ſore matter in this Generation that theſe three <hi>Harmonies</hi> is gone, and away in our <hi>Practice. Our</hi> doing <hi>the Duties of the First Table of the Law,</hi> wrongs and Juſtels againſt <hi>the Duties of the Second Table of the Law;</hi> and our <hi>doing the Duties of the Second Table,</hi> wrongs and juſtels againſt <hi>the Duties of the Firſt.</hi> For in <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of our <hi>Duties,</hi> many times we aim at GODs <hi>part,</hi> and leaves our own <hi>undone;</hi> or when we win any length in <hi>doing,</hi> we take all the Glory of it from GOD, to our ſelf; and our <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> thorturs our <hi>Light,</hi> and our <hi>Light</hi> thorturs our <hi>Doing.</hi> O Sirs, and it were kent how much we have thortured with GOD, we would be a Wonder to our ſelves; we have thortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with GOD, and we have thortured with the <hi>Light</hi> in our boſom; and we have thortured one with another; and we have thortured with the <hi>Bible;</hi> and in our <hi>Doings</hi> we are like to thorture with all the <hi>Testimonies of the Saints;</hi> we are a ſhamed, ſhamed, ſhamed Pack: there is nothing but thortur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among us.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Fifth</hi> Piece of <hi>Doing</hi> that the <hi>Christian</hi> is to ſtudy in his Generation at the back of <hi>Hearing of CHRISTs Sayings,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Christian</hi> is to mark his ſhort-comings of his <hi>Duties,</hi> and Mourn over them; and mark his ſpeed-comings, and bleſs GOD over theſe, and take an Argument from both to foſter <hi>doing</hi> upon his hand: Is not that a piece of Royal-work in a day of the <hi>Croſs?</hi> Therefore whenever a <hi>Miniſter</hi> hath preached up my <hi>Duty,</hi> I never reſt untill I win at <hi>doing,</hi> and I will not let GOD want neither the Glory of my ſhort-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, nor of my ſpeed-comings; and I bleſs GOD for that, and Ille take an Argument from both to feed <hi>doing</hi> and <hi>hearing</hi> u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon my hand. The Men of the World ſayes, <hi>What have we adoe with Religion now?</hi> It is ill ſpoken off every-where?
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171666:9"/>Ille tell you News; Ille get as much in the <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> and in <hi>Doing,</hi> as will keep me warm againſt the coldeſt blaſt that can blow upon the <hi>Christians</hi> in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Many thinks it is their <hi>Duty</hi> to grow <hi>Lukewarm</hi> in GODs Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and they call that <hi>Prudence.</hi> The <hi>Lukewarmneſs</hi> that GOD hath ſaid, <hi>He will ſpue out of his Mouth;</hi> Men and Women will call that <hi>prudence:</hi> Shame and lack come upon that <hi>prudence.</hi> GOD will tirll us out of that <hi>prudence</hi> ere He hath done with us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> This <hi>doing</hi> is a <hi>doing</hi> wherein the <hi>Christian</hi> is much troubled with the Bands that lyes upon his Spirit, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders him from <hi>doing</hi> what he would, for the want of encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>doing,</hi> are ſtaps in his Way; The Bands on his Spirit troubles him more than the want of the bleſſing and imbrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and dandling on the Knee of his <hi>Maſter</hi> here away: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hath a ſore heart; Why? not becauſe he wants the Countenance of his <hi>Maſter.</hi> But would ye ken what aills him? Here is his Complaint, Alas! <hi>I do nothing in Doing;</hi> the Bands on my Spirit makes me have a ſore heart. What aills thee, <hi>O Chriſtian,</hi> to break thy Heart? Is it for fear thou be not well, or is it for fear thou win not to heaven? Or is it for fear thou never be admitted to follow the <hi>Lamb</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove? Or is it becauſe thou gets not anew of His Viſits upon the Earth? No. What aills thee then poor Body? Alas it is becauſe I do nothing at the <hi>Doing-Trade,</hi> and that breaks my Heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> It is ſuch a <hi>doing</hi> as has theſe five <hi>Motives</hi> cleaving to it; O ken ye the five <hi>Motives</hi> of the <hi>Doing-Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt <hi>Motive</hi> of this <hi>Doing-Chriſtian,</hi> is this. He does timouſly; no ſooner is his Heart warmed <hi>with the hearing of CHRISTs Sayings;</hi> (but if I may ſay ſo) his fect is as ſoon warmed with the <hi>Practice</hi> of them, preſently he puts them in <hi>Practice;</hi> he never lets his heart cool, till he practiſe them;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171666:9"/>Well kens he to ſtrick the iron while it is hot. I wat not Sirs, I trow many of us lets our ſelves cool, ere ever we put CHRISTs <hi>Sayings in Practice.</hi> What is the reaſon that there are ſo many ſtiffe lithed Profeſſors in <hi>Scotland;</hi> Here is the Reaſon, we gate a kindly heat; but alas! we got a ſudden and unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cool upon the back of it. A ſudden cool upon the back of a great heat, makes Folk ſtiffe bound and ſweer to gang: We got a kindly heat under out ſwearing of a <hi>Covenant,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>a Work of Reformation,</hi> and a lively <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> But alas! we put it not in <hi>Practice,</hi> when it was at our heart; but we ſat down upon it, and that gave us a ſudden cool at the back of our heat, and that makes our Bones ſtiff; we dow not draw a Limb to us. O the ſudden cools that the <hi>Miniſters</hi> &amp; <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> hath given themſelves, that makes them Walk in the Ways of GOD, as if all their Bones were broken: Even like a poor <hi>Traveller</hi> hot on his Journey, and when he meets his Neighbour in the gate, he ſays to him, ſit down Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop and reſt you there; and the poor Man having ſitten a while, when he riſes, he dow not draw a Leg after him. O Sirs! it cannot be told how many makes ſtiff Bones among you; that that makes them Walk as if all their Bones were broken: But the Man that is an acceptable <hi>Doer,</hi> he does timouſly upon the back of <hi>Hearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Second <hi>Motive</hi> of this <hi>Doing-Man,</hi> and that is, As he does <hi>timouſly,</hi> ſo he does <hi>orderly;</hi> he begins with <hi>Subſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als,</hi> and for <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> he puts them in their own place, though he will leave none of them <hi>undone:</hi> He begins with that, that is firſt in GODs <hi>Count-book,</hi> and for other <hi>doings,</hi> he puts theſe in their own Room: Therefore it is a well wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed word of <hi>Davids</hi> in the 119. Pſalm, <hi>Order my Goings in Thy Way, and I ſhall keep Thy Teſtimonies to the end.</hi> I cannot tell what to do, nor what to begin at; bat if Thou wilt order my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, I will keep Fyle and Rank to purpoſe. But
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171666:10"/>O but the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> is ill <hi>Sojors</hi> in this <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-Warfare,</hi> for they can neither keep Fyle nor Rank; What will word of you Sirs? Will ye not all be broken?</p>
            <p>A Third <hi>Motive</hi> of this <hi>Doer,</hi> and that is, He will not be holden back from <hi>doing,</hi> neither by Friends nor Foes: And therefore, when he ſets to his <hi>Duty,</hi> will he let Fleſh and Blood hinder him; No. In that firſt of the <hi>Galatians</hi> 16. Verſe, immediatly ſaid the Apoſtle, <hi>I conſulted not with Fleſh and Blood: Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> will never be the <hi>Members</hi> of His <hi>Parliament,</hi> he will conſult none with them about the Buſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but he will ſet all theſe once to the Door. Will he not let the Counſel <hi>of Chriſtian-Friends</hi> hinder him? No. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that 21. Chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> 13. Verſe, <hi>What mean ye to Weep and break my Heart</hi> (ſays the Apoſtle) <hi>I am not only ready to go to Jeruſalem and be bound; but to Die for the Name of the LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> Woes me! are there not enew to break our Hearts, albeit <hi>Chriſtian-Friends</hi> break not our Hearts; <hi>I am-not only ready to gang to Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem for my Duty; but to Sacrifice my Life for that Cauſe that I Preach:</hi> Therefore the poor Man gangs in the Bands of the Spirit to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> knowing nothing but one thing, that in every Place and Country that he geed to, he was ay for to get a ſore skin; but he could promiſe himſelf no other Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs: This is ay the Comfort that a poor <hi>Miniſter</hi> hath to gang out and preach to a People and Country-ſide. Would ye ken what he can promiſe himſelf? nothing: But this, he is ſure of the fury of the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> in the Place he comes to, and he is ſure of the fury of the <hi>Curate</hi> in the Pariſh; and he is ſure of the fury of a whean <hi>Graceleſs Folk;</hi> and he is ſure of the Cenſure of a whean <hi>Old Jobb-trot-Chriſtians</hi> that hath joined with the <hi>Curats,</hi> and if there be any Dunts in dealing, he will get his ſhare of them; yet go they muſt, and do their <hi>Duty</hi> they muſt. I think and <hi>Paul</hi> had lived in our Time, he had been the rankeſt Fool that ever ran thereout. What can
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171666:10"/>ye promiſe to your ſelf <hi>Paul,</hi> in following out of your <hi>Duty? Bands and Afflictions in every place,</hi> I can promiſe my ſelf that, and a redding ſtroak ay when Dunts comes a Dealing; Will thou gang Man for all that? yes, Gang I muſt; I ken no other faer, yet gang I muſt, though the Spirit binds Hands and Feet; and when the Spirit binds, I dar not louſe. And as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſays, and O but he Reaſons well; <hi>What am I</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that I ſhould withſtand GOD,</hi> in that 11. of the <hi>Acts</hi> 17. Verſe. They are ay abuſing him for going to preach in that place and neock of the Country where they thought he had no Warrand to gang and preach; but he lets them all hear in the deafeſt ſide of their heads, that he had a Warrand to gang there; <hi>Who am I, that I ſhould withſtand GOD?</hi> Let all the Prudent Men in the Country-ſide Anſwer this, and Ille quatt the Buſſineſs.</p>
            <p>A Fourth <hi>Motive</hi> of this <hi>Doing-Man,</hi> and that is, He does <hi>conſtantly;</hi> ye will never find him out of <hi>doing;</hi> it may be he be put far from his Point, and may be he be put far from his Intention; but be put als far from it as he will, he falls ay a <hi>doing</hi> again. Well then, my Advice to you Sirs, is this, that ye fall a <hi>doing</hi> with it, and Labour twelve hours, <hi>for the Night cometh, when no Man ſeeth to Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> It is ſuch a <hi>Doing</hi> wherein four pieces of <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al-Wiſdom</hi> kyths in all his <hi>Doings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Firſt <hi>Practice of Doing,</hi> wherein <hi>Spiritual-Wiſdom</hi> kyths, is this, That any Attainment that he gets, and any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt that he receives from his <hi>Maſter</hi> for it, he puts ay a prize upon it, and bleſſes his <hi>Maſter</hi> for it; but he ſo puts a prize upon it as undervalues himſelf, and gives himſelf that Name in the 17. of <hi>Luke</hi> 10. Verſe, <hi>An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprofitable Servant;</hi> that ſhall evermore be my Name.</p>
            <p>A Second <hi>Practice of Wiſdom</hi> this <hi>Doer</hi> hath, and that is, He gives ay the <hi>Sayings of CHRIST</hi> a right Seat, and then
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:171666:11"/>when it hath a <hi>Right Seat,</hi> it will break out in many Springs. <hi>What is the Right Seat of the Sayings of CHRIST? David</hi> kent well what it was; The Right Seat of the Word of GOD, <hi>I hid Thy Word in my Heart,</hi> that is a Right Seat <hi>for the Sayings of CHRIST:</hi> Even the Heart of the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and having it well ſeated there, it will convey Streams through all his Members. A <hi>Right ſeated word of CHRIST</hi> will break out at the Eye; and a <hi>right ſeated word</hi> at the Heart will break forth at the Door; and a <hi>right ſeated word</hi> at the Heart, will break forth at the Mouth, and at the Hand, and Foot, and will convey it ſelf into all the Members: It cannot be told how many Streams the right placing of a word at the Heart will have.</p>
            <p>A Third <hi>Practice of Wiſdom</hi> this <hi>Doer</hi> hath, and that is, as he Places the Word of Chriſt Right in his Heart, ſo he plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf Right, and giveth CHRIST the Chief Room; and as long as ye give not Him the Chief Place and Room, ye will be but Bumblers at <hi>doing:</hi> Therefore this <hi>Doer,</hi> he ſets ay CHRISTs Chair at the Table-head, and when he hath ſet Him there, he hath <hi>three words</hi> to hear: O ken ye the <hi>three words</hi> the <hi>Doing-Christian</hi> hath in the day that he hath CHRIST ſet at the <hi>Table-head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>First word</hi> he hath, is this, <hi>LORD, What wilt Thou have me to do?</hi> The <hi>Second word,</hi> is this, <hi>LORD, help me to do.</hi> The <hi>Third word,</hi> is this, <hi>Not unto me, not unto me, but unto Thy Name be all the Glory:</hi> When ever he wins any bit forward in <hi>doing,</hi> then he ſays, <hi>Not unto me, not unto me; but to Thy Name be all the Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Fourth <hi>Practice of Wiſdom</hi> this <hi>Doer</hi> hath, and that is, He takes ay GODs <hi>March-ſtones,</hi> and GODs <hi>March-dyke</hi> to be the <hi>Rule</hi> of his <hi>Duties doing</hi> in <hi>Practice,</hi> and no other: Therefore it is not what <hi>March-stones</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> and the <hi>Lairds</hi> hath ſet to be the <hi>Rule</hi> of my <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Duty;</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:171666:11"/>and it is not what <hi>March-ſtones</hi> this <hi>Prelate</hi> and that <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> hath ſet, that is the <hi>Rule</hi> of my <hi>Dutie.</hi> But it is what <hi>March-ſtones</hi> the LORD Himſelf has ſet. Wad ye ken one of CHRISTs <hi>March-ſtones,</hi> there it is, <hi>Be ye Holy as I am Holy,</hi> 1 Peter 1.16. Vow Sirs, but that is a long <hi>March-dyke,</hi> there is many Aikers of Land within that <hi>March-dyke:</hi> O Sirs, there is meikle Work within that <hi>March-stone;</hi> keep your ſelves within it, and follow no Mans <hi>March-ſtones:</hi> but as I Walk, Walk ye.</p>
            <p>The next Thing to be ſpoken to, is this, Wherein lyes the <hi>Commendableneſs</hi> of this to be <hi>doing</hi> at the back of <hi>hearing of CHRISTs Sayings:</hi> And <hi>First,</hi> The <hi>Commendableneſs</hi> of it lyes in this, this is the thing, to be <hi>doing</hi> at the back of <hi>hearing</hi> that hath <hi>Bleſsedneſs</hi> intailled on it, John 13.17. <hi>Happy are ye if ye know theſe things; but bleſsed are ye if do them.</hi> But <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Commendableneſs</hi> of it lyes in this, this is the thing that Honours your <hi>Maſter,</hi> this is the Exerciſe that puts Reſpect and Honour upon CHRIST. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> The <hi>Commendableneſs</hi> of it lyes in this, That this is the Exerciſe that will not only make thee to fend under the <hi>Croſs,</hi> but out-live it with <hi>Commendation;</hi> this will put thee in a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to out-live a <hi>Storm</hi> with <hi>Commendation.</hi> The Men of the World ſayes, <hi>That they will make a Storm and Streſs of Weather blow all our Religion from us yet;</hi> but I hope to ſee them all beguiled. But they ſay, <hi>They ſhall gar a New Storm blow our Giddy-headedneſs and Phanatiziſm from us, and they ſhall blow a Covenant and a Work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from us.</hi> Indeed there is over many hath this blown from them; but brag at leaſnre, the <hi>Doing-Chriſtian</hi> ſhall keep <hi>his Religion, his Godlineſs, and his Covenant,</hi> and ye ſhould gang to the <hi>ſorrow:</hi> Ye may win to my Eſtate, and to my Body; but for <hi>my Religion,</hi> ye ſhall never win at that: Ye may gar me leave Houſe and Family, and may make me
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171666:12"/>bide many a cold blaſt, or ye may uncover my Roof, &amp; ſend all my Bairns a begging; but for the bony Houſe that I have been Building under a <hi>Lively Miniſtry,</hi> ye ſhall never get a hole in that; for the bony bit Houſe that they call <hi>Religion,</hi> which I have been making up under a <hi>Covenant, and Work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> there ſhall never a drop of Rain win in that Houſe, come the Floods as they will; and there ſhall never an air of Wind win in, in that Houſe blow from what airt it will: Ye ſhall never ſee a hole in the Wall of that Houſe, and ye ſhould wait while your Eyes rote out of your Head. But <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The <hi>Commendableneſs</hi> of it lyes in this, That of all Men and Women in the World, the Man and the Woman that is <hi>Doers</hi> at the back of <hi>hearing,</hi> is bulk ſomeſt in CHRISTs boſom, and is not that a <hi>Commendable-Exerciſe,</hi> that makes me ſo bulk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom to Him? It is a fore matter, Sirs, we cannot be bulkſom in our <hi>Maſters</hi> boſom in thir Days. Well then, Ille tell you what we will Reſolve on, we will Reſolve <hi>to be Doers of Chriſts Sayings,</hi> and then we ſhall throw His Grace be bulkſome in GODs Sight, and this will pay home the loſs of the little bulk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſs we have among them whom we live among.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> Ay the more thou ſtudies <hi>doing</hi> at the back of <hi>hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> the more thou keeps a <hi>Good Conſcience:</hi> For as long as thou keeps this Diſh upon thy Table, heartſom muſt thy Life be; for thou hath a Diſh upon thy Table that all the <hi>Prelats</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> hath not the like of it. Thou that hath broked <hi>thy Religion by doing,</hi> hath a bra Diſh upon thy Table; if ſo be thou hath been at <hi>a doing of CHRISTs Sayings,</hi> thou hath a bra Life of it. But I think there are many of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsors of Scotland,</hi> hath tryed the <hi>doing</hi> of many Aſſayings, that is not <hi>CHRISTs Sayings:</hi> For they have tryed <hi>Popery,</hi> and they have tryed <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi> and they have tryed <hi>a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion;</hi> and now they are at <hi>Atheiſm</hi> where they began, and I think that they ſhall be there. Well Sirs, <hi>Doing</hi> at
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171666:12"/>the back of <hi>Hearing</hi> is heartſom, and if ye <hi>hear</hi> but little <hi>do</hi> the more; and if ye be <hi>Doers</hi> of the thing that ye <hi>Hear,</hi> this <hi>Doing</hi> ſhall bring more to your Hand, and ye ſhall yet gang on Graſs to your Eyen Holes, for the bare going ye have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; ſo do and wait for Him in His own Way, and ye ſhall have a brave Life of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let us pray</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
